<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="5.0" xml:id="desc-101064">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>National Library of Sweden, A 14</title>
            <sponsor ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100151">Medieval Latin Manuscripts in the National Library: Cataloguing and Digitization</sponsor>
            <sponsor ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100004">National Library of Sweden</sponsor>
            <funder ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100003">Riksbankens jubileumsfond – The Swedish Foundation for Humanities and Social Sciences</funder>
            <respStmt>
               <resp key="cataloguer"/>
               <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100485">Anna Wolodarski</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp key="cataloguer"/>
               <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100483">Erika Kihlman</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>manuscripta.se: A Digital Catalogue of Medieval and Early Modern Manuscripts in Sweden</publisher>
            <idno type="URI" subtype="Manuscripta">https://www.manuscripta.se/desc/101064</idno>
            <date when="2022"/>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en" resp="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100483">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100081">Sweden</country>
                  <settlement ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100078">Stockholm</settlement>
                  <institution ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100004">National Library of Sweden</institution>
                  <repository ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100040">National Library of Sweden</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">A 14</idno>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno type="id" subtype="Libris">p4487z6pm8n1bhf2</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno type="id" subtype="Regina">004837577</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno type="URI" subtype="Manuscripta">https://www.manuscripta.se/ms/101064</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Acts and proceedings from the canonization process of Saint Birgitta of Sweden</head>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <p>
                              <locusGrp>
                                 <locus from="LCI" to="LCI" scheme="other"/>
                                 <locus from="RCI" to="RCI" scheme="other"/>
                              </locusGrp>
                              <material>Parchment</material>
                           </p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure type="leftFlyleaves" quantity="0" unit="folios"/>
                           <measure type="rightFlyleaves" quantity="0" unit="folios"/>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation>Foliation 1-255 by modern hand in pencil takes account of the two inserted leaves at the back.  </foliation>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p>
                        <locus from="RCI" to="RCI" scheme="other"/>
                        <note>Medieval shelfmark "F I 4us"; four contemporary folio references to mentions of Katarina; four Latin words scribbled in lower right corner; the letter "G" in the lower left corner. </note>
                     </p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        <p>Binding from <placeName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100101">Vadstena</placeName> House (of an older type?), very torn brown leather over wooden boards; 4 double spinebands and 2 endbands, the covering is cracking along the spine edge and part of it is missing at the head and tail; two metal plates with fragments of straps at the fore-edge; the straps are lost; metal pins project through the back cover; nails under the cover in the corners of the boards near the spine edge recognisable; a title label of parchment written in ink, located in the centre section of the back board, worn, text partly erased: Attestaciones b---/ F I; shelfmark F I in black ink even near the upper edge of the back board. Quire central folds reinforced by blank parchments strips.</p>
                        <p>
                           <dimensions type="binding">
                              <height quantity="295" unit="mm"/>
                              <width quantity="210" unit="mm"/>
                              <depth quantity="75" unit="mm"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>Written by Italian scribes c. <origDate when="1391">1391</origDate> in <origPlace>
                        <placeName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100070">Rome</placeName>
                     </origPlace>, see Collijn 1924-1931, pp. iv-vii, xiv.</origin>
                  <provenance>Library of the <placeName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100101">Vadstena</placeName>monastery, shelf mark F I 4us on the paste down of the back cover, F I on the back cover and the remnants of the shelf mark on the title label F---. </provenance>
                  <provenance>To the Royal Chancery in 1620 and in the 1670s to the <orgName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100059">Antikvitetskollegiet</orgName>, see Collijn 1924-31, pp. v-vii, who lists the manuscript in different inventories of Antikvitetskollegiet / Antikvitetsarkivet, shelfmark SKB U 90-91. The manuscript listed in U 90:4 as 74, the number visible on the second panel of the spine, in U 91:2:1 as G 74, letter G at the bottom of the paste down of the back cover, in U 91:3 as number 6, inscribed on 1r.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>To the <orgName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100004">National Library</orgName> from <orgName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100059">Antikvitetsarkivet</orgName>: Berch’s catalogue, shelfmark A 14. </acquisition>
               </history>
               <msPart>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <idno type="codicologicalUnit">1</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                     <msItem class="acta">
                        <locus from="1v" to="23v" scheme="folios"/>
                        <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                        <title type="uniform" xml:lang="la">Summary of the canonization process of Saint Birgitta of Sweden</title>
                        <rubric xml:lang="la">Rubricacio seu summa. Rubricacio seu summa tocius processus canonizacionis beate Brigide de Swecia</rubric>
                        <incipit defective="false">In nomine yhesu christi Misericordis et pii Ac eius Virginis matris et Beati Jeronimi Amen. QVia dominus noster papa et Collegium Cardinalium multis et arduis que in Romane curie alueum vndique confluunt quasi torrens ...</incipit>
                        <explicit defective="true">... ixl dies accedentibus uero singulis infra octauas dei festi ad sepulchrum ipsum. xl. dies de iniuncta sibi penitencia misericorditer Relaxamus.</explicit>
                        <note>
                           <p>
                                                                                The rubric is inscribed on f. 1v in a high, compressed and elaborate style. The upper parts of the letters in "beate" are missing due to tear in the leaf.
                                                                            
                                                                            
                                                                       
                                                                       
                                                                  
                                                                  
                                                             
                                                             
                                                        
                                                        
                                                   
                                                   
                                              
                                              
                                         
                                         
                                    </p>
                           <p>
                              <locusGrp>
                                 <locus from="1r" to="1r" scheme="folios"/>
                                 <locus from="22v" to="23v" scheme="folios"/>
                              </locusGrp> are blank.
                                                                            
                                                                            
                                                                       
                                                                       
                                                                  
                                                                  
                                                             
                                                             
                                                        
                                                        
                                                   
                                                   
                                              
                                              
                                         
                                         
                                    </p>
                        </note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <supportDesc material="paper">
                           <support>
                              <p>
                                 <locus from="1r" to="23v" scheme="folios"/>
                                 <material>Western paper</material>
                                 <watermark n="1">
                                    <locusGrp>
                                       <locus from="1" to="20" scheme="folios"/>
                                    </locusGrp>
                                    <term type="watermarkMotif">Balance (closest to Briquet 2373).</term>
                                 </watermark>
                                 <watermark n="2">
                                    <locusGrp>
                                       <locus from="23" to="23" scheme="folios"/>
                                    </locusGrp>
                                    <term type="watermarkMotif">Hunting horn (closest to Briquet 7672).</term>
                                 </watermark>
                                 <dimensions type="leaf">
                                    <height quantity="295" unit="mm"/>
                                    <width quantity="225" unit="mm"/>
                                 </dimensions>
                              </p>
                           </support>
                           <extent>
                              <measure type="textblockLeaves" quantity="23" unit="folios"/>
                           </extent>
                           <foliation>Contemporary foliation (by same scribe as some of the marginal notes?) in the upper right corner of recto i-xxi (ff. 2-22); foliation xviiii-xxi by a different hand (main scribe?); f. 23 is blank without original foliation; leaf numbering in red in the lower left corner of each verso in the form of letters a-r and numbers ii-xv starts on f. 3v (a i was probably in the lower corner of f. 2 but is now lost); ff. 3-21 have pagination in pale leadpoint in the middle of the lower margin, a 4-a 40 visible.
                                        Secundo folio: eorundem et in specie.
                                    </foliation>
                           <condition>The lower quarter of f. 1 is missing (no text-loss); a horisontal tear from the outer edge one quarter down on the page, ca 8 cms in length, affecting both f. 1 and f. 2.</condition>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="29 32" ruledLines="">
                              <locus from="1r" to="23v" scheme="folios"/>
                              <dimensions type="written">
                                 <height quantity="180" unit="mm"/>
                                 <width quantity="115" unit="mm"/>
                              </dimensions>
                           </layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote xml:id="hand-1" sameAs="">Gothic cursive</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <p>
                           <locus from="2r" to="2r" scheme="folios"/>
                           <note>The words "Acta et processus Canonizationis S. Birgittae de Suecia" have been added in the top margin by an early modern hand.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <locus from="2r" to="22r" scheme="folios"/>
                           <note>Marginal notes and manicules added on almost every page by the main hand and at least one other, contemporary, hand.</note>
                        </p>
                     </additions>
                     <decoDesc>
                        <p/>
                        <decoNote type="initials">f. 2r: 4-line outline initial with a simple vegetative ornament on the stems and bows in the counter spaces; ff. 2r and 21v: two 2-line initials with faces in the counter spaces; f. 19r: 3-line initial with simple vegetative ornament in the counter space.</decoNote>
                     </decoDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history/>
               </msPart>
               <msPart>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <idno type="codicologicalUnit">2</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                     <msItem class="acta">
                        <locus from="24r" to="123v" scheme="folios"/>
                        <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                        <title type="uniform">Acts and proceedings from the canonization process of Saint Birgitta of Sweden</title>
                        <rubric>Acta et processus habitus coram Reuerendissimis in christo patribus dominis Gradensi Corphiensi et de zangro Cardinalibus Commissarijs super negocio Canonizacionis Beate Brigide de Regno Swecie</rubric>
                        <incipit xml:lang="la" defective="false">In nomine domini Amen Anno a natiuitate eiusdem Millesimo Tricentesimo Septuagesimo nono. Jndiccione secunda die Jouis tercio mensis marcij ponit sanctissimj in christo patris et domini nostri domini vrbani diuina prouidencia pape sexti Anno primo. In mei notarij publici et testium infrascriptorum presencia discretus vir Nereus Nerey Cursor et magister Cursorum domini nostri pape ... </incipit>
                        <explicit xml:lang="la" defective="false">... vt predictorum copiam dicto sindico et procuratori et quibuscumque alijs eam petentibus et habere volentibus trademur predictorum petencium sumptibus et expensis.</explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Et sic est finis productorum.</finalRubric>
                        <note>Below final rubric is written: Jncipiunt attestaciones testium productorum et receptorum in Roma super sancto Canonizacionis pie memorie domine Brigide de Regno Swecie. Continuando folium sequens et cetera. </note>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem class="test">
                        <locus from="124r" to="250v" scheme="folios"/>
                        <title type="uniform">Attestations from individual witnesses</title>
                        <rubric xml:lang="la">Incipiunt deposiciones testium productorum et receptorum in Roma Super articulis et miraculis pie memorie domine Beate Brigide de Regno Swecie ac Super negocio canonisacionis ipsius et cetera.</rubric>
                        <incipit defective="false">In christi nomine Amen sequuntur attestaciones testium productorum super vita conuersacione et miraculis recolende memorie domine Brigide ... </incipit>
                        <explicit defective="false">... Cetera vero signa et sigilla dictis scripturis appensa et consignata dixit ipse testis illis sibi exhibitis non cognoscere. </explicit>
                        <finalRubric>Et sic sit finis huiusmodi processus et cetera. laus christo et gloria per seculorum secula Amen. </finalRubric>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem class="epist">
                        <locus from="250v" to="253r" scheme="folios"/>
                        <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                        <title type="uniform" xml:lang="la">Supplication letters for the canonization process of Saint Birgitta</title>
                        <rubric xml:lang="la">littere supplicatorie pro Canonizacione beate Brigide. </rubric>
                        <incipit defective="false">Hic sequuntur tres littere Supplicatorie directe domino vrbano pape vj pro Canonizacione beate Brigide de quibus fit mencio supra folio xxiijj in margine hoc est Cxiiii. Sanctissimo in christo patri ac domino domino suo Carissimo domino vrbano ...</incipit>
                        <explicit defective="false">... sic eciam ad placandam diuine maiestatis offensam suis sanctis precibus esse dignetur patrona misericors et favorabilis advocata. Datum Orabro Strengianensis diocesis Anno ab incarnacione Millesimo CCC Septuagesimo nono xviij die mensis Januarii sub Sigillis nostris.</explicit>
                        <note>The words "hoc est Cxiiii" are an addition to the incipit by another hand, after which a space of ca four lines has been left blank. Below last line of the explicit the phrase "hoc est die prisce virginis" is added.</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <supportDesc material="paper">
                           <support>
                              <p>
                                 <locus from="24r" to="253v" scheme="folios"/>
                                 <note>Tabs on fols 124, 144, 168, 172, 192. </note>
                                 <watermark n="1">
                                    <locusGrp>
                                       <locus from="24r" to="183v" scheme="folios"/>
                                    </locusGrp>
                                    <term type="watermarkMotif">Axe (closest to Briquet 7503).</term>
                                 </watermark>
                                 <watermark n="2">
                                    <locusGrp>
                                       <locus from="162r" to="253v" scheme="folios"/>
                                    </locusGrp>
                                    <term type="watermarkMotif">Two circles (closest to Briquet 3169).</term>
                                 </watermark>
                                 <material>Western paper</material>
                                 <dimensions type="leaf">
                                    <height quantity="295" unit="mm"/>
                                    <width quantity="225" unit="mm"/>
                                 </dimensions>
                              </p>
                           </support>
                           <extent>
                              <measure type="textblockLeaves" unit="folios" quantity="230"/>
                           </extent>
                           <foliation>Contemporary foliation i-clix (ff. 24-182); clxx-ccxxix (ff. 183-252; clxx erroneously corrected (to clxi ?); clx-clxix skipped incorrectly; leaf numbering in red in the lower outer corner of the verso-side starts on f. 24v (b vii) and continues throughout until f. 252v.
                                        Secundo folio: Reuerendis patribus.
                                    </foliation>
                           <condition>Bottom outer corners of ff. 252-253 detached, no text-loss. Two lengthwise tears on f. 253. </condition>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" ruledLines="" writtenLines="33 40">
                              <locus from="24r" to="253v" scheme="folios"/>
                              <dimensions type="written">
                                 <height min="245" max="250" unit="mm"/>
                                 <width unit="mm" min="140" max="145"/>
                              </dimensions>
                           </layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote xml:id="hand-2">Gothic cursive</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <p>
                           <locus from="24r" to="253r" scheme="folios"/>
                           <note>Marginal notes, "nota"-signs and manicules passim; running title and subtitles added in top margin by contemporary hand beginning on fol. 24r: "Atestationes [sic] Deposicio domini cardinalis Theatini". </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <locus from="253v" to="253v" scheme="folios"/>
                           <note>An end-title, "processus canonizacionis beate brigide de swecia", is added by the same hand and in the same style as on f. 1v. In the upper left-hand corner references to specific passages are written by a contemporary hand. </note>
                        </p>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msPart>
               <msPart>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <idno type="codicologicalUnit">3</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                     <msItem class="hagiogr">
                        <locus from="254r" to="254v" scheme="folios"/>
                        <title type="uniform">Collection of miracles concerning saint Birgitta</title>
                        <incipit>Margareta filia haraldi muratoris et uxoris eius cecilie de ciuitate stocholmiensi Vpsalensis [post corr. ex strengnensis] dyocesis ceca nata mansit in eadem cecitate per dimidium annum …</incipit>
                        <explicit defective="false">... statim surgentes exierunt per medias plateas et portas ciuitatis ita secure quod nullus eis verbum contrarium loqueretur Hi anno domini M:o ccc xc:o in ascensione domini ad monasterium watzstenense venientes hoc iuramento prestito ad [post corr. ex et] sancta ewangelia firma constancia asserebant. </explicit>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <supportDesc material="paper">
                           <support>
                              <p>
                                 <locus from="254r" to="254v" scheme="folios"/>
                                 <material>Western paper</material>
                                 <dimensions type="leaf">
                                    <height quantity="285" unit="mm"/>
                                    <width quantity="205" unit="mm"/>
                                 </dimensions>
                                 <note>This leaf is an insertion in the volume.</note>
                              </p>
                           </support>
                           <extent>
                              <measure type="textblockLeaves" unit="folios" quantity="1"/>
                           </extent>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="33 35">
                              <locus from="254r" to="254v" scheme="folios"/>
                              <dimensions type="written">
                                 <height quantity="220" unit="mm"/>
                                 <width min="170" max="180" unit="mm"/>
                              </dimensions>
                           </layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote xml:id="hand-3">Gothic cursive</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                     <additions>
                        <p>
                           <locus from="254r" to="254r" scheme="folios"/>
                           <note>Two words added in the bottom margin in an early modern hand: "Finis ---(?)".</note>
                        </p>
                     </additions>
                  </physDesc>
               </msPart>
               <msPart>
                  <msIdentifier>
                     <idno type="codicologicalUnit">4</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                     <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                     <msItem>
                        <locus from="255r" to="255r" scheme="folios"/>
                        <title type="desc">Instruction from cardinal Lucas de Gentilibus concerning the examination of the miracles</title>
                        <rubric>Notabile qualiter et quomodo miracula sanctorum debeant examinari</rubric>
                        <incipit>Modus tenendus super eo quod queritur a me videtur michi quod debeat esse talis videlicet ... </incipit>
                        <explicit defective="false">... et isti procuratores dicta miracula sic autentico modo conscripta Remittant ad dictum dominum episcopum et monasterium quolibet anno certo tempore.</explicit>
                     </msItem>
                     <msItem class="acta">
                        <locus from="255v" to="255v" scheme="folios"/>
                        <title type="uniform">List of witnesses in the canonization process</title>
                        <rubric>Testes producti notabiles ad deponendum de articulis per [post corr. ex pro?] procuratores (?) vel commissarios (?) exceptos (?) pro canonizacione beate birgitte</rubric>
                        <note>At the bottom of the page a folio reference to the supplication letters (ff. 250v-253r) has been added by a different, contemporary hand: "littere supplicatorie pro canonizacione beate birgitte folio xix".</note>
                     </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <supportDesc material="paper">
                           <support>
                              <p>
                                 <locus from="255r" to="255v" scheme="folios"/>
                                 <dimensions type="leaf">
                                    <height quantity="230" unit="mm"/>
                                    <width quantity="185" unit="mm"/>
                                 </dimensions>
                                 <material>Western paper</material>
                                 <note>This leaf is an insertion in the volume.</note>
                              </p>
                           </support>
                           <extent>
                              <measure type="textblockLeaves" unit="folios" quantity="1"/>
                           </extent>
                        </supportDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout columns="1" writtenLines="32">
                              <locus from="255r" to="255r" scheme="folios"/>
                              <dimensions type="written">
                                 <height quantity="220" unit="mm"/>
                                 <width min="140" max="150" unit="mm"/>
                              </dimensions>
                           </layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <handDesc>
                        <handNote xml:id="hand-4">Gothic cursive</handNote>
                     </handDesc>
                  </physDesc>
               </msPart>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change status="draft"
                 when="2022-07-08"
                 who="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100380">First draft</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <p/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
