<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="5.0" xml:id="desc-101059">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>National Library of Sweden, A 201</title>
                <sponsor ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100151">Medieval Latin Manuscripts in the National Library: Cataloguing and Digitization</sponsor>
                <sponsor ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100004">National Library of Sweden</sponsor>
                <funder ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100003">Riksbankens jubileumsfond – The Swedish Foundation for Humanities and Social Sciences</funder>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="editor"/>
                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100380">Patrik Granholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="cataloguer"/>
                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100483">Erika Kihlman</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>manuscripta.se: A Digital Catalogue of Medieval and Early Modern Manuscripts in Sweden</publisher>
                <idno type="URI" subtype="Manuscripta">https://www.manuscripta.se/desc/101059</idno>
                <date when="2022"/>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc resp="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100380" xml:lang="en">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100081">Sweden</country>
                        <settlement ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100078">Stockholm</settlement>
                        <institution ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100004">National Library of Sweden</institution>
                        <repository ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100040">National Library of Sweden</repository>
                        <idno type="shelfmark">A 201</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="id" subtype="Libris">grl65cgjdt96k6sj</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="id" subtype="Regina">004676168</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="URI" subtype="Manuscripta">https://www.manuscripta.se/ms/101059</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head>Sermons and miscellaneous theological texts</head>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc form="codex">
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="RCI" to="RCI" scheme="other"/>
                                        <material>Parchment</material>
                                    </p>
                                </support>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="leftFlyleaves" unit="folios"/>
                                    <measure type="rightFlyleaves" unit="folios"/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation>Modern foliation in pencil 1-146. <secFol>diuine laudis</secFol>
                                </foliation>
                                <collation>
                                    <formula>1-11(8), 12(6, lacks 4-6), 13(8, lacks 1), 14-19(8).</formula>
                                    <p>
                                        <ref target="https://vceditor.library.upenn.edu/project/69f9cbda6e6f4a0001f9b83b/viewOnly">VisColl collation</ref>
                                    </p>
                                    <signatures>Quire signatures in black ink on the verso of the last leaf of quires 1-11, the last one on <locus from="88v" to="88v" scheme="folios"/>. </signatures>
                                    <catchwords>Catchwords on the last leaf of quires 1-11, 13-14, and 16-18. </catchwords>
                                </collation>
                                <condition>The paste down on <locus from="LCI" to="LCI" scheme="other"/> is missing. Remnants of its text visible as an off-set print.</condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <additions>
                            <p>
                                <locus from="LCI" to="LCI" scheme="other"/>
                                <note>Top left corner: National Library book label with the current signum in black ink.</note>
                            </p>
                        </additions>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding contemporary="true">
                                <p>Medieval binding. Brown leather over wooden boards. 3 double raised bands and 2 endbands. 2 hooked clasps attached to red leather straps. 2 catchplates on <locus from="LCO" to="LCO" scheme="other"/>. On <locus from="Spine" to="Spine" scheme="other"/> stamped in gold: <quote>A 201</quote>. On <locus from="LCO" to="LCO" scheme="other"/> two paper labels with text in black ink (barely readable due to wear): <quote>Exempla sanctorum et miracula et primo de beata virgine maria Sermones breues de tempore Sermo de passione domini cum aliis. Exposicio dominice oracionis et alia multa</quote>; on the second label an old signum, <quote>I 14</quote>, or (<quote>F 14</quote>) corrected to <quote>I 15</quote> which is written both on the label and on the cover.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <dimensions type="binding">
                                        <height quantity="222" unit="mm"/>
                                        <width quantity="165" unit="mm"/>
                                        <depth quantity="70" unit="mm"/>
                                    </dimensions>
                                </p>
                                <condition>The brown colour of the leather is worn off in places. Spine is cracked, now reinforced with linen fabric. The pastedown on <locus from="LCI" to="LCI" scheme="other"/> is missing, leaving the board attachments visible. The leather on <locus from="RCO" to="RCO" scheme="other"/> is cracked.</condition>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <p>
                                <origPlace cert="low">
                                    <placeName cert="low" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100104">Germany</placeName>
                                </origPlace>, <origDate notAfter="1450" notBefore="1351">14th-century, late, to 15th century, early</origDate>. Origin and dating based on the script, exact origin and date unknown.</p>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance>
                            <p>Belonged to the Erfurt Charterhouse as evidenced by the addition in the upper margin on <locus from="1r" to="1r" scheme="folios"/>: <quote>Cartusie Erfordiensis</quote>.</p>
                        </provenance>
                        <acquisition>
                            <p>Purchased from <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/101069">George Stephens</persName> 23 October 1848 as evidenced by the addition in the lower right corner on <locus from="1r" to="1r" scheme="folios"/>: <quote xml:lang="sv">Inköpt till Kgl. Bibl. från G. Stephens 23/10 1848</quote>.</p>
                        </acquisition>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl>
                                <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107582">Leclercq (1950)</title>
                                <citedRange from="126" to="126" unit="page"/>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl>
                                <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107421">Lehmann (1935)</title>
                                <citedRange from="12" to="14" unit="page"/>
                            </bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <idno type="codicologicalUnit">1</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="1ra" to="83ra" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Sermones de tempore</title>
                                <rubric>prima dominica in aduentu</rubric>
                                <incipit>Hora est iam nos de sompno surgere Ad Ro xiii In hac epistula invitat nos apostolus ad quatuor Primo monet de sompno surgere</incipit>
                                <explicit>primus panis carnalis uel corporalis secundus racionalis tercius spiritualis et cetera</explicit>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="83rb" to="90va" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Martyrdoms of saints</title>
                                <rubric>Incipit de sanctis</rubric>
                                <incipit>Nota quod mortes sanctorum et tribulaciones vindicantur Mors domini uindicatur a tyto et vespasiano</incipit>
                                <explicit>Katherina habet in multis tribulacionibus subuenire et cetera.</explicit>
                                <finalRubric>Expliciunt auctoritates de sanctis per manus</finalRubric>
                                <note>Martyrdoms of the following saints: Andrew, Nicholas, Lucy, Thomas (apostle), John, Thomas Becket, Silvester, Paul of Thebes, Gregory, Benedict, Patrick, George, Adalbert, Mark, Philip (apostle), James the Minor, Pancras, Gervasius and Protasius, John the Baptist, John and Paul, Peter (apostle), Paul (apostle), Margaret, Mary Magdalene, Martha, Cyriacus, Lawrence, Bartholomew, Giles, Matthew, Maurice, Cosmas and Damian, Wenceslaus, Stanislaus, Jerome, Denis, Leonard, ten thousand martyrs, Simon and Jude, Martin, Elizabeth, Cecilia, Clemens, and Catherine.</note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="90vb" to="91rb" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">On sins</title>
                                <incipit>Gregorius dicit missa dum cantetur peccata tam viuorum tam mortuorum condonantur </incipit>
                                <explicit>quia missa inuita audita ualet ad dimissionem culpe ad remissionem pene et ad augmentum gracie et cetera </explicit>
                                <note>Also in Köpenhamn, <orgName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100007">Royal Danish Library</orgName>, Gl. kgl. S. 1360 4o, f. 24v.</note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="91v" to="91v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">A brief text on sins and a list of the ten commandments </title>
                                <rubric>Nota peccata clamancia</rubric>
                                <note>These two texts are probably additions to an otherwise blank page. The first text begins: <quote>Nota peccata clamancia Sunt tria que numquam cessant clamare</quote>. The second begins: <quote>Nota decem precepta ydola sperne dei nomen non</quote>.</note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="92r" to="113v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">On the passion of Christ</title>
                                <explicit>ab eo duplici stola inmortalitatis videlicet corporis et anime decorari et regnum eternum cum ipso possidere Quod nobis prestare dignetur ipse dominus noster Ihesus christus qui cum patre et sancto spiritu viuit et regnat deus per omnia secula seculorum Amen</explicit>
                                <finalRubric>Explicit sermo de passione totali domini nostri ihesu christi</finalRubric>
                                <note>The beginning of the text is missing on account of at least one missing leaf. It probably contained a prologue since the first extant rubric, on <locus from="92r" to="92r" scheme="folios"/> reads: <quote>de prima parte</quote>. The second part begins on <locus from="101r" to="101r" scheme="folios"/>, the third part on <locus from="106r" to="106r" scheme="folios"/> and the fourth part on <locus from="110r" to="110r" scheme="folios"/>. Parts 2-4 account for each hour of Christ's passion with the hours added in red in the outer margin.</note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="113v" to="114r" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">On sins</title>
                                <incipit>Sanctus bernardus dicit quot octo sunt que a peccatis nos reuocant et sunt de essencia hominis que si homo diligenter consideraret in eternum non peccaret</incipit>
                                <explicit>temptacionum feruor utriusque hominis statum affixerit Eligamus pocius ardere quam cedere</explicit>
                                <note>The beginning of the text is a paraphrase of a passage in <bibl>
                                        <title type="uniform" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107248">Jacobus de Voragine's Legenda aurea</title>
                                        <citedRange from="13" to="13" unit="chapter"/>
                                        <citedRange from="156" to="158" unit="number"/>
                                    </bibl>, <quote>De circumcisione domini</quote>. The end of the text is a citation from <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102595">Bernard of Clairvaux</persName>, <quote>In vigilia nativitatis domini</quote>, Sermo III, <bibl>
                                        <title ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107595">PL</title>
                                        <citedRange from="97b" to="97b" unit="column"/>
                                    </bibl>.</note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="114r" to="114v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">On the passion of Christ</title>
                                <incipit>Qualiter per memoriam passionis domini nostri ihesu christi repellitur temptacio Nota bene</incipit>
                                <explicit>id est in speculacione videbis quod nobis prestare dignetur pater et filius et spiritus sanctus Cottidie igitur predicta in corde tuo permeditare</explicit>
                                <note>In the margin is added in black ink by a contemporary hand: <quote>Memoria passionis christi</quote>.</note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="115r" to="131v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Collection of excerpts</title>
                                <rubric>Incipiunt notabilia bona</rubric>
                                <incipit>Hec sunt quindecim signa ante diem Iudicii que erunt In quindecim diebus que beatus Ieronimus invenit in libris ebreorum</incipit>
                                <explicit>Item securis siue ferrum supernatans aquam et sic est finis et cetera</explicit>
                                <note>This section contains 44 <quote>notabilia</quote> treating for instance the dignity of priests, confession, Mass, the conversion of sinners, the seven deadly sins, the gospels. The first text is the list of the fifteen signs before Judgement and <quote>15 signa</quote> has been added in the outer margin by a contemporary hand. The last text is on the efficacy of prayer, with the heading <quote>De oracione notabile bonum</quote>.</note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="132r" to="134r" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">On the twelve degrees of humility (Excerpts from the Rule of St Benedict)</title>
                                <rubric>De duodecim gradibus humilitatis</rubric>
                                <incipit>Clamat nobis scriptura diuina fratres dicens omnis qui se exaltat humiliabitur (Luke 8:14)</incipit>
                                <explicit>Ideo angustam viam arripuit et cetera</explicit>
                                <note>Listed in <bibl>
                                        <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107423">Bloomfield et al. (1979)</title>
                                        <citedRange from="824" to="824" unit="number"/>
                                    </bibl>. The first section, <locus from="132r" to="133v" scheme="folios"/>, is Ch. 7 of <bibl>
                                        <title ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107603">The Rule of St Benedict</title>
                                    </bibl>. The last section, <locus from="133v" to="134r" scheme="folios"/>, is an excerpt from the beginning of Ch. 5. In the top margin on <locus from="132r" to="132r" scheme="folios"/> is added in red ink by a contemporary hand: <quote>De gradibus humilitatis</quote>. </note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="134r" to="134r" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Two excerpts from Jerome and Gregory</title>
                                <incipit>Beatus Ieronimus Monachus viuat in monasterio sub vnius disciplina patris</incipit>
                                <explicit>Vna quippe et summa est probacio karitatis si et ipse diligitur qui aduersatur</explicit>
                                <note>The first text is taken from <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102780">Pseudo-Jerome</persName>
                                    <quote>Homilia ad monachos</quote>, <bibl>
                                        <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107596">PL 30</title>
                                        <citedRange from="313A" to="313B" unit="column"/>
                                    </bibl>. The second consists of passages excerpted from <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102527">Gregory I</persName>, <quote>Homilies on the Gospels</quote>, <quote>Homily</quote> 15, <bibl>
                                        <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107597">PL 76</title>
                                        <citedRange from="1133C" to="1205D" unit="column"/>
                                    </bibl>.</note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="134v" to="135v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Minus speculum peccatoris </title>
                                <rubric>Redite preuaricatores ad cor (Isa. 46:8)</rubric>
                                <incipit>Vacate et videte quoniam ego sum deus (Ps. 45:11) ysaye xlvi Ineffabilis diuine bonitatis dignacio que cottidie conspicit nos infelices</incipit>
                                <explicit>ut obitum beatum obtines et pervenias ad locum Inmortalitatis et felicitatis ac Iocunditatis eterne et cetera</explicit>
                                <finalRubric>Explicit mynus speculum peccatoris et cetera</finalRubric>
                                <note>In the upper margin is added in black ink by a contemporary hand: <quote>Minus speculum peccatoris ex dictis sancti bernhardi</quote>. Listed in <bibl>
                                        <title ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107423">Bloomfield</title>
                                        <citedRange from="5119" to="5119" unit="number"/>
                                    </bibl>. This text is usually ascribed to Augustine but here, as in the manuscript <ref target="https://www.manuscripta.se/ms/101174">Stockholm, Kungliga biblioteket, MS A 198</ref>, f. 157r-158v, to <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102595">Bernard of Clairvaux</persName>. Between the end of the text proper and the final rubric is a short text marked in the outer margin with <quote>nota bene</quote> and beginning <quote>Flos monachorum ad cor redeas Vide quid agas</quote> and ending <quote>Mentem compone perfeccioni stude deum time <sic>ut</sic> iudicem dilige ut patrem</quote>. </note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="136r" to="140v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <author>
                                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102694">Pseudo-Bernard</persName>
                                </author>
                                <title type="desc">Formula honestae vitae with added excerpts</title>
                                <rubric>Formula beati bernhardi de vita et honestate</rubric>
                                <incipit>Petis a me frater karissime quod numquam et nusquam a suo provisore audiui petiuisse </incipit>
                                <explicit>lis in capitulo dissolucio in chor Irreuerencia circa altare hoc hugo de claustro anime et cetera et sic est finis huius</explicit>
                                <note>The text of <quote>Formula honestae vitae</quote> as printed in <bibl>
                                        <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107598">PL 184</title>
                                        <citedRange from="1167C" to="1170C" unit="column"/>
                                    </bibl>, ends on <locus from="137v" to="137v" scheme="folios"/> where <quote>nota bene</quote> has been added in both the inner and the outer margin in black and red ink respectively. Thereafter, follow short excerpts on themes such as the perfection of religious life, contempt for the world, and the value of correction, each introduced by a rubric in red or by the words <quote>nota bene</quote>. The last excerpt is from Ch. 11 of <quote>De claustro animae</quote> by <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102722">Hugh of Fouilloy</persName>. On <locus from="140v" to="140v" scheme="folios"/> the original final rubric in red, <quote>Explicit tractatus vtilis videlicet formula beati bernhardi de vita et honestate</quote>, has been struck through with black ink. On <locus from="138r" to="138r" scheme="folios"/> is added in black ink by a contemporary hand: <quote>explicit formula bernhardi</quote>. </note>
                                <bibl>
                                    <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107598">PL 184</title>
                                    <citedRange from="1167C" to="1170C" unit="column"/>
                                </bibl>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="141r" to="146v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Treatise on the Eucharist</title>
                                <rubric>Incipit tractatus bonus de sacramento eukaristie</rubric>
                                <incipit>Mare non habundat tot guttis sol splendoribus nec silue frondibus </incipit>
                                <explicit>tentus non dimittatur donec in amoris cubiculum mansurus introducatur et cetera</explicit>
                                <finalRubric>Explicit tractatus bonus de sacramento eukaristie et cetera</finalRubric>
                                <note>This treatise seems to consist of two excerpts. The first one ending on <locus from="145v" to="145v" scheme="folios"/> and the second one beginning on <locus from="146r" to="146r" scheme="folios"/> where <quote>Item de sacramento</quote> is written in red in the upper margin.</note>
                            </msItem>
                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <objectDesc>
                                <supportDesc material="paper">
                                    <support>
                                        <p>
                                            <locus from="1" to="146" scheme="folios"/>
                                            <material>Paper</material>
                                            <watermark n="1">
                                                <locusGrp>
                                                    <locus from="1" to="91" scheme="folios"/>
                                                </locusGrp>
                                                <term type="watermarkMotif">Circle with single-line rod. </term>
                                                <note>Only parts of the watermark is visible in the upper margin.</note>
                                            </watermark>
                                            <watermark n="2">
                                                <locusGrp>
                                                    <locus from="92" to="146" scheme="folios"/>
                                                </locusGrp>
                                                <term type="watermarkMotif">Oxhead with single rod.</term>
                                                <note>The watermark is in the gutter and only partially visible.</note>
                                            </watermark>
                                            <dimensions type="leaf">
                                                <height quantity="205" unit="mm"/>
                                                <width quantity="150" unit="mm"/>
                                            </dimensions>
                                        </p>
                                    </support>
                                    <extent>
                                        <measure type="textblockLeaves" quantity="146" unit="folios"/>
                                    </extent>
                                    <foliation>Contemporary foliation in upper margin in ink 1-91, 95-149. The original ff. 92-94 and one unfoliated leaf have been ripped out.</foliation>
                                    <condition>Four leaves ripped out between <locus from="91" to="91" scheme="folios"/> and <locus from="92" to="92" scheme="folios"/>. An unknown number of quires are missing after <locus from="146v" to="146v" scheme="folios"/>.</condition>
                                </supportDesc>
                                <layoutDesc>
                                    <layout columns="2" ruledLines="31">
                                        <locus from="1r" to="8v" scheme="folios"/>
                                        <dimensions type="written">
                                            <height quantity="160" unit="mm"/>
                                            <width quantity="50" unit="mm"/>
                                        </dimensions>
                                        <note>Ruling in ink. Prickings in the margins.</note>
                                    </layout>
                                    <layout columns="2" ruledLines="28">
                                        <locus from="9r" to="91v" scheme="folios"/>
                                        <dimensions type="written">
                                            <height quantity="155" unit="mm"/>
                                            <width quantity="50" unit="mm"/>
                                        </dimensions>
                                        <note>Ruling in ink. Prickings in the margins.</note>
                                    </layout>
                                    <layout columns="1" writtenLines="36 39">
                                        <locus from="92r" to="146v" scheme="folios"/>
                                        <dimensions type="written">
                                            <height unit="mm" max="155" min="150"/>
                                            <width unit="mm" max="110" min="100"/>
                                        </dimensions>
                                        <note>Guidelines in ink. Text written above the top line and sometimes also below.</note>
                                    </layout>
                                </layoutDesc>
                            </objectDesc>
                            <handDesc>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-1">
                                    <locus from="1r" to="51v" scheme="folios"/>Cursiva antiquior. Possibly a new hand on <locus from="50va" to="50va" scheme="folios"/>.</handNote>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-2">
                                    <locus from="51vb" to="56ra" scheme="folios"/>Cursiva antiquior.</handNote>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-3">
                                    <locus from="56rb" to="56rb" scheme="folios"/>Cursiva antiquior with occasional loopless ascenders. </handNote>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-4">
                                    <locus from="56va" to="91rb" scheme="folios"/>Cursiva antiquior. Possibly a new hand on <locus from="77va" to="77va" scheme="folios"/> and on <locus from="83va" to="83va" scheme="folios"/>.</handNote>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-5">
                                    <locus from="91v" to="91v" scheme="folios"/>Textualis. </handNote>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-6">
                                    <locus from="92r" to="114v" scheme="folios"/>Cursiva antiquior.</handNote>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-7">
                                    <locus from="115r" to="140v" scheme="folios"/>Cursiva antiquior. </handNote>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-8">
                                    <locus from="141r" to="146v" scheme="folios"/>Cursiva antiquior. Possibly a new hand on <locus from="146r" to="146r" scheme="folios"/>.</handNote>
                            </handDesc>
                            <additions>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="1r" to="1r" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Upper margin in black ink by a later hand: <quote>Cartusie Erfordiensis</quote>; ca eight words by a contemporary hand but struck-through and only partially readable due to wear of the paper, the last words being <quote>scilicet in ultimo folio</quote>. In bottom margin in black ink, struck-through, by a contemporary hand: <quote>Sermones de tempore hora est iam nos et in fine priuilegia sanctorum</quote>; in light brown ink two illegible words have been added by a contemporary hand; in bottom right corner in black ink by a 19th-century hand: <quote>Inköpt till Kgl. Bibl. från G. Stephens 23/10 1848</quote>.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="1r" to="145r" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Nota-signs, manicules and short additions throughout, e.g. <locus from="27r" to="27r" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="56v" to="56v" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="96v" to="96v" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="106r" to="106r" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="143r" to="143r" scheme="folios"/>. On <locus from="111v" to="111v" scheme="folios"/> a longer addition in the outer margin which seems to have once been covered by a glued-on paper (?) slip, now lost.</note>
                                </p>
                            </additions>
                            <decoDesc>
                                <p>Main text in black ink, rubrics in red or underlined or struck-through in red. Capitals touched in red. Plain initials over two lines in red.</p>
                                <decoNote type="bookmarks">
                                    <p>Bookmarks on <locus from="50" to="50" scheme="folios"/> (red parchment), <locus from="63" to="63" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="74" to="74" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="82" to="82" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="113" to="113" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="131" to="131" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="134" to="134" scheme="folios"/>, and <locus from="140" to="140" scheme="folios"/> (all in white parchment).</p>
                                </decoNote>
                            </decoDesc>
                        </physDesc>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="published" when="2026-06-03" who="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100483">First published 260603</change>
            <change status="draft" when="2022-06-23" who="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100380">First draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
