<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="5.0" xml:id="desc-101175">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>National Library of Sweden, A 199</title>
                <sponsor ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100151">Medieval Latin Manuscripts in the National Library: Cataloguing and Digitization</sponsor>
                <sponsor ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100004">National Library of Sweden</sponsor>
                <funder ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100003">Riksbankens jubileumsfond – The Swedish Foundation for Humanities and Social Sciences</funder>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="editor"/>
                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100380">Patrik Granholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="cataloguer"/>
                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100484">Robin Böckerman</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>manuscripta.se: A Digital Catalogue of Medieval and Early Modern Manuscripts in Sweden</publisher>
                <idno type="URI" subtype="Manuscripta">https://www.manuscripta.se/desc/101175</idno>
                <date when="2023"/>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc resp="robibock" xml:lang="en">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100081">Sweden</country>
                        <settlement ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100078">Stockholm</settlement>
                        <institution ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100004">National Library of Sweden</institution>
                        <repository ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100040">National Library of Sweden</repository>
                        <idno type="shelfmark">A 199</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="id" subtype="Libris">1gw5qqr5zb0k24vb</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="id" subtype="Regina">004846338</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="URI" subtype="Manuscripta">https://www.manuscripta.se/ms/101175</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head>Henricus de Frimaria, Tractatus de decem preceptis; Expositio salutationis angelicae. Thomas ab Aquino, De rationibus fidei</head>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc form="codex">
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="RCI" to="RCI" scheme="other"/>
                                        <note>
                                            <locus from="LCI" to="LCI" scheme="other"/>: the flyleaf has been removed but the text on it has left an offprint.</note>
                                        <material>Parchment</material>
                                        <dimensions type="leaf">
                                            <height quantity="195" unit="mm"/>
                                            <width quantity="140" unit="mm"/>
                                        </dimensions>
                                    </p>
                                </support>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="leftFlyleaves" unit="folios"/>
                                    <measure type="rightFlyleaves" unit="folios"/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation>Modern foliation in pencil (from <locus from="55" to="105" scheme="folios"/> the foliation has been corrected). <secFol>ad deum in montem</secFol>
                                </foliation>
                                <collation>
                                    <formula>1-5(10), 6(1+10), 7-9(8), 10(1+1+1+4), 11(12+1)</formula>
                                    <p>
                                        <ref target="https://vceditor.library.upenn.edu/project/69ce52206e6f4a0001f9744e/viewOnly">VisColl collation</ref>. Structure of quire 10 tentative, most likely it originally conisted of 8 leaves, but three of the remaining leaves are today almost detached. Parchment guards at the centre of each quire, and between first and second quire.</p>
                                    <catchwords>
                                        <locus from="10v" to="50v" scheme="folios"/>: Catchwords written inside a single or double frame with red ink strike-through. </catchwords>
                                </collation>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <additions>
                            <p>
                                <locus from="LCI" to="LCI" scheme="other"/>
                                <note>Upper left corner, National Library book label.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <locus from="RCI" to="RCI" scheme="other"/>
                                <note>Top of page, in black ink by a medieval hand: <quote>Ad carthusienses prope erffordiam</quote>; right margin, written perpendicular to the previous text:<quote> Theodericus de luneborg leuoldi procurator</quote>; the pastedown also contains some scribblings or pen-trials by a medieval hand.</note>
                            </p>
                        </additions>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding contemporary="true">
                                <p>
                                    Medieval binding. Red leather over bevelled wooden boards. 4 double raised bands and endbands. Brass hook and clasp. <locus from="LCO" to="LCO" scheme="other"/>, in ink by a medieval hand on a parchment label: <quote>Super x precepta exposicio Henrici de Frimaria Exposicio bona valde super dominicam oracionem et angelicam salutacionem Thomas de racionibus fidei Methodius et cetera</quote>; beneath, traces of a removed label. <locus from="Spine" to="Spine" scheme="other"/>, traces of a removed label; fragments of an old label; stamped in gold: <quote>A 199</quote>.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="RCI" to="RCI" scheme="other"/>: pastedown consist of a fragment from a theological manuscript. The side facing out is blank, but the leaf is partially detached from the cover and text on the other side is visible in the lower left corner. The same leaf is visible on <locus from="Stub_1" to="Stub_1" scheme="other"/>.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <dimensions type="binding">
                                        <height quantity="195" unit="mm"/>
                                        <width quantity="150" unit="mm"/>
                                        <depth quantity="50" unit="mm"/>
                                    </dimensions>
                                </p>
                                <condition>Leather worn and very faded. Boards exposed at corners. Endbands exposed. The <locus from="RCO" to="RCO" scheme="other"/> is full of holes from bookworms.</condition>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <p>
                                <origPlace>
                                    <placeName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100104">Germany</placeName>
                                </origPlace>, <origDate notAfter="1500" notBefore="1401">15th century</origDate>. The manuscript carries owner's notes by the<orgName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100182"> Carthusians</orgName> in <placeName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100224">Erfurt</placeName>, who may also have written the manuscript.</p>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance>
                            <p>According to the note on <locus from="RCI" to="RCI" scheme="other"/>, <locus from="1r" to="1r" scheme="folios"/>, and <locus from="Note_1r" to="Note_1r" scheme="folios"/> the manuscript belonged to the <orgName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100182">Carthusians</orgName> in <placeName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/place/100224">Erfurt</placeName>.</p>
                        </provenance>
                        <provenance>
                            <p>The manuscript was sold at auction in <date when="1836"/> as part of the library of book collector <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102541">Friedrich Gottlieb Julius von Bülow</persName>. Presumably, it had come into von Bülow's possession earlier in the 19th century, when the charterhouse was secularized. In von Bülow's collection the manuscript was listed as <quote>no. 447</quote> and in the Carthusian collection as <quote>H. 29</quote> (see <bibl>
                                    <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107421">Lehmann (1935)</title>
                                    <citedRange from="6" to="6" unit="page"/>
                                </bibl>).</p>
                        </provenance>
                        <acquisition>
                            <p>Purchased by the <orgName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/org/100004">National Library</orgName> from<persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/101069"> George Stephens</persName> in <date when="1848"/>. </p>
                        </acquisition>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl>
                                <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107421">Lehmann (1935)</title>
                                <citedRange from="6" to="7" unit="page"/>
                            </bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <idno type="codicologicalUnit">1</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <summary>
                                <p>The manuscript is missing the last quires. If the medieval list of content on <locus from="1r" to="1r" scheme="folios"/> is correct the manuscript is missing around 10 texts.</p>
                            </summary>
                            <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="1r" to="54r" scheme="folios"/>
                                <author>
                                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102697"> Henricus de Frimaria </persName>
                                </author>
                                <title type="desc">De decem preceptis</title>
                                <rubric>Prologus</rubric>
                                <incipit>Audi israel precepta domini et ea in corde tuo (Deu. 4:1) <gap reason="editorial"/> In verbis propositis spiritus sanctus circa diuina precepta tria tangit </incipit>
                                <explicit>quod vinum nobis meritis gloriose virginis prestare dignetur eius filius benedictus qu cum patre et spiritu sancto est vnus deus benedictus in secula seculorum amen</explicit>
                                <bibl>
                                    <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107586">Guyot (2005)</title>
                                </bibl>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="54r" to="61r" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Table of content</title>
                                <incipit>Vt autem in isto tractatu contenta legenti promptius occurant hinc est quod puncta nobiliora in presenti tabula seriatim tulis designare</incipit>
                                <explicit>Explicit tabula super tractatum decem preceptorum editum pro instructionem simplicium ad laudem dei et profectum animarum Cui sit honor et gloria per infinita secula seculorum Amen </explicit>
                                <note>
                                    <p>
                                        The table of content is introduced by a short introduction, which is then followed by a list of chapters and subchapters keyed to the text with letters that are found in the margin of the text.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="61v" to="61v" scheme="folios"/>: blank.</p>
                                </note>
                            </msItem>
                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <objectDesc>
                                <supportDesc material="paper">
                                    <support>
                                        <p>
                                            <locus from="1" to="61" scheme="folios"/>
                                            <material>Paper</material>
                                            <dimensions type="leaf">
                                                <height quantity="195" unit="mm"/>
                                                <width quantity="140" unit="mm"/>
                                            </dimensions>
                                            <note>Parts of one or two large watermarks visible on the upper part of the leaves, e.g. <locus from="5" to="5" scheme="folios"/> and <locus from="61" to="61" scheme="folios"/>.</note>
                                        </p>
                                    </support>
                                    <extent>
                                        <measure type="textblockLeaves" quantity="61" unit="folios"/>
                                    </extent>
                                    <foliation>
                                        <locus from="1" to="54" scheme="folios"/>: contemporary foliation 1-54, and some sort of chapter markers with letters and Roman numerals. </foliation>
                                    <condition>Paper stained in many places.</condition>
                                </supportDesc>
                                <layoutDesc>
                                    <layout columns="1" writtenLines="32 34">
                                        <dimensions type="written">
                                            <height quantity="155" unit="mm"/>
                                            <width quantity="90" unit="mm"/>
                                        </dimensions>
                                        <note>Guidelines in ink.</note>
                                    </layout>
                                </layoutDesc>
                            </objectDesc>
                            <handDesc>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-1">
                                    <locus from="1r" to="61r" scheme="folios"/>Gothic cursiva antiquior (both looped and unlooped ascenders occur). <!--(or textualis currens?)--></handNote>
                            </handDesc>
                            <additions>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="Note_1r" to="Note_1r" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Small paper note stored in a modern envelope. The text is a list of content written by a medieval hand: <quote>hic liber est fratrum carthusiensium prope erffordiam Contenta henricus de frimaria circa X precepta cum triplici sensu cuiuslibet cum tabula in fine eiusdem tractatus Exposicio bona dominice oracionis Similiter super angelicam salutacionem secundum sensum literalem et misticam Et videntur ambe eiusdem henrici de Frimaria Tractatus beati Thome de Racionibus fidei ad cantorem Anthiocenum Aliqua capitula pulcra de sancta trinitate et de verbo patris Sumpta ex libro beato Thome de fide spe et caritate </quote>.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="Note_1v" to="Note_1v" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Same hans as on the recto: <quote>hic liber est fratrum carthusiensium prope Erffordiam Contenta hic </quote> (the last two words smudged or erased).</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="1r" to="1r" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Top margin (to the right of the rubric <quote>Prologus</quote>): <quote>Hic sunt hec de decem preceptis cum tabula sua in fine Item Exposicio super pater noster bona Amen Item Exposicio super Ave maria Vrimariensis Item tractatus beati thome de racionibus fidei </quote> (to the left of <quote>Prologus</quote> with a signe-de-renvoi): <quote>Idem de fide spe et caritate Item liber de adam et eua Item de david Item de nativitate marie et assumpcione eius Oracio de corpore Christi Item Methodius liber eius Item sermo de nativitate christi Item de ultimo iudicio et de 15 signis et de antichristo Item de sancto paulo </quote> (below the phrase <quote>de primo</quote> with a signe-de-renvoi:) <quote>apostolo scilicet eius conversione Item casus episcopales et aliorum Item de Confessione et cetera Item de vestibus sacerdotalibus ?et alia scil. super? Missam albertus magnus </quote>. Bottom margin, in pencil by a modern hand: <quote>Cartusiae
                                            Erfordiensis</quote>; below, in ink by a modern hand: <quote>inköpt till Kgl. Bibl. fr G. Stephens 23/10 1848</quote>.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="1r" to="61r" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Framed tituli and keywords by the scribe in the marigins and marginal additions by at least one contemporary hand.</note>
                                </p>
                            </additions>
                            <decoDesc>
                                <p>Main text in brown ink, capitals touched in red, lemma underlined in red.</p>
                                <decoNote type="initials">
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="1r" to="60v" scheme="folios"/>: plain initials over 2-4 lines in red.</p>
                                </decoNote>
                                <decoNote type="bookmarks">
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="33" to="33" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="38" to="38" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="45" to="45" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="49" to="49" scheme="folios"/>, <locus from="51" to="51" scheme="folios"/>: bookmarks in red paper glued to the page.</p>
                                </decoNote>
                            </decoDesc>
                        </physDesc>
                        <history/>
                    </msPart>
                    <msPart>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <idno type="codicologicalUnit">2</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="62r" to="84r" scheme="folios"/>
                                <author>
                                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102697"> Henricus de Frimaria </persName>
                                </author>
                                <title type="desc">Exposicio oracionis dominice</title>
                                <rubric>Incipit exposicio oracionis dominice</rubric>
                                <incipit>PAter noster Hinc dominice oracioni beatus gregorius premittit prefacionem </incipit>
                                <explicit>qui cum patre et spiritu sancto viuit et regnat deus gloriosus per infinita secula seculorum amen </explicit>
                                <finalRubric>Explicit exposicio oracionis dominice </finalRubric>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="84v" to="85r" scheme="folios"/>
                                <author>
                                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102607"> Peter Lombard </persName>
                                </author>
                                <title type="desc">Excerpt from The Sentences</title>
                                <rubric>Explicit expo<supplied reason="omitted">sicio</supplied> liber primus sententiarum Distinctio I<hi rend="super">a</hi>
                                </rubric>
                                <incipit>Augustinus de doctrina christiana liber primus </incipit>
                                <explicit>longe melior qui fecit vtrumque</explicit>
                                <note>
                                    <p>
                                        Excerpts from Distincio 1-3 of the Sentences, Book 1.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="85v" to="85v" scheme="folios"/>: blank.</p>
                                </note>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="86r" to="92v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <author>
                                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102697"> Henricus de Frimaria </persName>
                                </author>
                                <title type="desc">Expositio salutationis angelice </title>
                                <rubric>Incipit exposicio salutacionis angelice secundum duplicem sensum litteralem videlicet et misticum edita per magistrum de vrymaria</rubric>
                                <incipit>Qvia oracionem dominice secundum ritum ecclesie et deuocionem fidelium</incipit>
                                <explicit>Quam desponsacionem nobis patrare? dignetur qui est benedictus in secula seculorum amen </explicit>
                                <finalRubric>Et in hoc terminatur exposicio salutacionis angelice ad honorem dei et gloriose virginis matris eius marie</finalRubric>
                            </msItem>
                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <objectDesc>
                                <supportDesc material="paper">
                                    <support>
                                        <p>
                                            <locus from="62" to="92" scheme="folios"/>
                                            <material>Paper</material>
                                            <dimensions type="leaf">
                                                <height quantity="195" unit="mm"/>
                                                <width quantity="140" unit="mm"/>
                                            </dimensions>
                                            <note>Parts of at least one type of watermark visible on the inner edge of the leaves, e.g. on <locus from="86" to="86" scheme="folios"/>.</note>
                                        </p>
                                    </support>
                                    <extent>
                                        <measure type="textblockLeaves" quantity="31" unit="folios"/>
                                    </extent>
                                    <condition>Leaves stained and ink smudged in places. <locus from="88v" to="89r" scheme="folios"/>: large red ink stain in the outer margin.</condition>
                                </supportDesc>
                                <layoutDesc>
                                    <layout columns="1" writtenLines="34 37">
                                        <dimensions type="written">
                                            <height quantity="160" unit="mm"/>
                                            <width quantity="120" unit="mm"/>
                                        </dimensions>
                                        <note>
                                            <locus from="86r" to="92v" scheme="folios"/>: guidelines in ink.</note>
                                    </layout>
                                </layoutDesc>
                            </objectDesc>
                            <handDesc>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-2">
                                    <locus from="62r" to="85r" scheme="folios"/>Textualis currens.</handNote>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-3">
                                    <locus from="86r" to="92v" scheme="folios"/>Gothic cursiva antiquior (both looped and unlooped ascenders occur).</handNote>
                            </handDesc>
                            <additions>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="62r" to="84r" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Additions by one or several contemporary hands in the margin. The additions consist of corrections, comments, and nota-marks.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="86r" to="92v" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Additions framed in red triangels by the scribe in the margins. The additions consist of summaries or key-words from the text. There are also additions by a second hand, e.g. on <locus from="90r" to="90r" scheme="folios"/>.</note>
                                </p>
                            </additions>
                            <decoDesc>
                                <p>Main text in black-brown ink, capitals touched in red, rubrics in red.</p>
                                <decoNote type="initials">
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="62r" to="62r" scheme="folios"/>: text opens with plain initials over 4 lines in red.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="63v" to="85r" scheme="folios"/>: plain initials over 2-3 lines in red.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="86r" to="86r" scheme="folios"/>: text opens with plain initials in red with some penwork over 5 lines.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="88r" to="91r" scheme="folios"/>: plain initials over 3-4 lines in red.</p>
                                </decoNote>
                                <decoNote type="bookmarks">
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="62" to="62" scheme="folios"/>: bookmarks in red paper glued to the page.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="86r" to="86r" scheme="folios"/>: tear after removed bookmark.</p>
                                </decoNote>
                            </decoDesc>
                        </physDesc>
                    </msPart>
                    <msPart>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <idno type="codicologicalUnit">3</idno>
                        </msIdentifier>
                        <msContents>
                            <textLang mainLang="la"/>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="93r" to="103v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <author>
                                    <persName ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/102691"> Thomas Aquinas </persName>
                                </author>
                                <title type="desc">De Rationibus Fidei ad Cantorem Antiochenum</title>
                                <rubric>Incipit tractatus sancti doctoris fratris thome de aquino ordinis predicatorum ad Cantorem antiocenum de racionibus fidei </rubric>
                                <incipit>Beatus petrus apostolus qui promissionem accepit ut super eius confessionem fundaretur ecclesia</incipit>
                                <explicit>tamen alibi sunt diligentius pertractata </explicit>
                                <finalRubric>Explicit auctoritas beati thome</finalRubric>
                                <bibl>
                                    <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107584">De rationibus fidei (1968)</title>
                                </bibl>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="103v" to="105r" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Excerpts from De fide</title>
                                <incipit>
                                    <supplied reason="omitted">B</supplied>Eatus thomas in libro de fide spe et caritate ad fratrem reynaldum capitulo 13<hi rend="super">a</hi>
                                </incipit>
                                <explicit>Latini dicunt tres personas greci vero tres ypostasis patrem et filium et spiritum sanctum et cetera </explicit>
                                <note>The text consist of De fide, chapter 38-50.</note>
                                <bibl>
                                    <title type="short" ref="https://www.manuscripta.se/bibl/107585">Compendium Theologiae (1979)</title>
                                </bibl>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem>
                                <locus from="105v" to="105v" scheme="folios"/>
                                <title type="desc">Treatise on the triangle and the Trinity</title>
                                <rubric>
                                    <del>Ad g-s</del> Nota exemplum trine vnitatis de triangulo </rubric>
                                <incipit>In figura vero relucet beate trinitatis similitudo </incipit>
                                <explicit>ipsi sint eadem superficies et sigillatim vnusquisque et in summo esse et cetera </explicit>
                            </msItem>
                        </msContents>
                        <physDesc>
                            <objectDesc>
                                <supportDesc material="paper">
                                    <support>
                                        <p>
                                            <locus from="93" to="105" scheme="pages"/>
                                            <material>Paper</material>
                                            <dimensions type="leaf">
                                                <height quantity="195" unit="mm"/>
                                                <width quantity="140" unit="mm"/>
                                            </dimensions>
                                            <note>Parts of one type of watermark, most likely a tower, visible on the inner edge of the leaves, e.g. <locus from="102" to="102" scheme="folios"/>.</note>
                                        </p>
                                    </support>
                                    <extent>
                                        <measure type="textblockLeaves" quantity="13" unit="folios"/>
                                    </extent>
                                    <condition>Leaves dirty and partially or fully detached from the binding. Several quires have been removed at the end, which has caused a break or gap in the inside of the spine. A booklet made of modern paper has been added for support (visible on <locus from="Fore-edge" to="Fore-edge" scheme="other"/>).</condition>
                                </supportDesc>
                                <layoutDesc>
                                    <layout columns="1" writtenLines="35 43">
                                        <dimensions type="written">
                                            <height unit="mm" max="165" min="160"/>
                                            <width unit="mm" max="120" min="95"/>
                                        </dimensions>
                                        <note>Guidelines in ink.</note>
                                    </layout>
                                </layoutDesc>
                            </objectDesc>
                            <handDesc>
                                <p/>
                                <handNote xml:id="hand-4">
                                    <locus from="93r" to="105v" scheme="folios"/>Gothic cursive. The text on these leaves varies a great deal in terms of ink and the size of the script. It may be written by several different hands, but it is also possible that it is the same scribe using different pens. </handNote>
                            </handDesc>
                            <additions>
                                <p>
                                    <locus from="93r" to="105v" scheme="folios"/>
                                    <note>Additions in the margins by at least two different contemporary hands. The additions consist of corrections, phrases such as <quote>Nota bene</quote> on <locus from="93v" to="93v" scheme="folios"/>, and comments on the state of the text, e.g. <locus from="94v" to="94v" scheme="folios"/>, bottom margin: <quote>hic ulla/-us deficit</quote>.</note>
                                </p>
                            </additions>
                            <decoDesc>
                                <p>Main text in brown ink, capitals touched in red, rubrics underlined in red.</p>
                                <decoNote type="initials">
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="93r" to="96r" scheme="folios"/>: plain initials over 2-3 lines in red.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="98r" to="105r" scheme="folios"/>: space reserved for initials, often with guide letters.</p>
                                </decoNote>
                                <decoNote type="bookmarks">
                                    <p>
                                        <locus from="93" to="93" scheme="folios"/>: bookmarks in red paper glued to the page.</p>
                                </decoNote>
                            </decoDesc>
                        </physDesc>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="published" when="2026-06-02" who="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100484">260602</change>
            <change status="draft" when="2023-10-22" who="https://www.manuscripta.se/person/100380">First draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
